MoMA PS1 Archives
The Museum of Modern Art, Publisher
MoMA PS1 Archives
19702009
19712005
The Museum of Modern Art. Museum Archives 11 West 53 Street New York, NY 10019-5497 Phone: (212) 708-9617 Fax: (212) 408-6385 Email: archives@moma.org
MoMA PS1
313.5 linear feet in: 713 5" manuscript boxes 1 12x12x15" record carton 3 16x20" flat boxes 1 5x12" card box 9 flat files
Institutional records of MoMA PS1 including records of its organization and founding in 1971 and records of its curatorial, press and communications, publications, studio program, development, and other major activities as well as records of the director and general administration files.
Historical Note
MoMA PS1 is an internationally known exhibition space dedicated to exploring new art and ideas in the unique environment of a rehabilitated 19th century school building. It is one of the oldest and largest nonprofit art spaces in the country and since its founding in 1971 has nurtured artists' careers through its studio program, introduced and promoted important artists through solo exhibitions and programs, and explored historical movements and emerging trends in the art world through large group exhibitions. Throughout its history PS1 has devoted significant space to photography, video, film, dance, performance, and other media, while continuing to champion the work of painters and sculptors. The history of MoMA PS1 as documented in the archives spans important eras in the New York art world and history, from the cultural rebirth of SoHo and the growth of commercial galleries in the 1970s, to the political and social turmoil of the 1980s, the internationalization of the art market and community in the 1990s and an era of new technological interconnectedness in the 2000s. Through each successive era PS1 has remained a vital center for contemporary art in New York City.
Following is a brief history of the institution. Researchers interested in the history of MoMA PS1 should also consult Archives' web pages, particularly the chronology of important events.
19711972: The Founding of the I.A.U.R.
The Institute for Art and Urban Resources (I.A.U.R.)the organization that would become MoMA PS1can trace its origin to before 1970. It was then Alanna Heiss worked in London for the organization S.P.A.C.E. securing derelict warehouse space in the St. Katherine Docks area for use as artist studios. Heiss returned to America intent on creating a similar program in New York City. By 1971, Heiss held the position of program director for the Municipal Arts Society of New York (MAS,) an organization dedicated to architectural preservation and urban planning. She was also part of a social circle of artists, many of whom were involved with 112 Greene Street, founded by Jeffrey Lew in 1970 and credited as the first non-profit art space.
In May 1971 Heiss organized for the MAS a series of concerts and events in City Hall Park to commemorate the birthday of the Brooklyn Bridge. At the same time she took advantage of nearby piers and space underneath the bridge to organize a much more informal three-day arts festival. She invited artist friends to install artworks onsite while others staged performances.The Brooklyn Bridge Event(May 21May 24, 1971) was soon considered the I.A.U.R.'s originating event, even though the organization would not be incorporated for another year.
Heiss began scouting properties that could be secured by the MAS and then sublet to artists, a program she christened Workspace. The first property that was taken possession of, in 1972, was a privately-owned warehouse at 10 Bleecker Street, between Elizabeth Street and Bowery in Manhattan. That May a solo show by the sculptor Richard Nonas became the I.A.U.R.'s second official exhibition. By August it had been decided that the MAS was not the best organization to administer Workspace and on August 7, 1972 articles of incorporation were signed for the Institute for Art and Urban Resources with Alanna Heiss as director.
19721976: Growth of the I.A.U.R.
The I.A.U.R. negotiated for other studio spaces in 1972 in addition to 10 Bleecker Street. The I.A.U.R. gained office space at 11 John Street in Manhattan; a set of spaces was secured for artists inside the 80th Police Precinct on Washington Avenue in Brooklyn; and an industrial space was leased from the city in Coney Island to serve as a sculpture workshop for a small number of artists including Jene Highstein and Richard Nonas. Alana Heiss also spent a significant portion of 1972 trying to unsuccessfully secure the large building #13 in the Brooklyn Navy Yard. And it is likely that by the end of 1972 negotiations for the Clocktower were already underway.
108 Leonard Street (346 Broadway) in lower Manhattan had been designed by McKim, Meade & White in 1870 and was topped by a clock tower accessible only by a spiral staircase from the building's thirteenth floor (itself accessible only by stairs.) The I.A.U.R. occupied the tower and adjoining spaces in 1973, named it the Clocktower Gallery, and opened the first exhibition Joel Shapiro: Sculpture on April 12th.
In the summer of 1973 more space had been gained when three adjacent properties at 22 Reade Street were secured from the city for studios and exhibition and performance space. It was christened the Idea Warehouse but it would not be the site of any public activity until early 1975. The most significant exhibition held there was the series of performances and exhibition Ideas at the Idea Warehouse(June 16July 11, 1975.)
Meanwhile the series of exhibitions Collectors of the Seventies had launched at the Clocktower with the first ever exhibition of works from the collection of Dorothy and Herb Vogel. There would be four more exhibitions and a set of nine documentary videos produced in the series. Also in spring of 1975 word was received that the First Ward school building, or Public School No. 1, in Long Island City, Queens, was possibly available for use.
1976: P.S. 1 and Rooms
The P.S.1 building had ceased being a school in 1963 and used only as storage by the city. By 1975 it was in danger of being sold and demolished. The negotiations for the I.A.U.R. to occupy P.S. 1 continued through the next year. Heiss had estimates prepared for the costs of cleaning and making minimal necessary repairs to the building and had secured funds to pay for the work. A twenty-year lease was signed on April 22nd and the first exhibition,Rooms(June 9June 26, 1976,) opened six weeks later. To stage the show the I.A.U.R. invited seventy-eight artists to participate, assigned or had them select a room or space in the building, and let them free to install work they brought in, build a new work on site, or alter the site to create a work. To celebrate the opening of the exhibition and the building, the I.A.U.R. staged a benefit gala, the P.S. 1 Prom, elected a prom king and queen (Herb and Dorothy Vogel) and had a high school band provide dance music. A catalogue documenting the exhibition was published nearly a year later.
After Rooms closed, many of the artists stayed and rented studio space in the building but the I.A.U.R. lacked a long-term plan for the building. The casual administration of the Workspace program had led to non-occupancy of supposedly rented-out space, non-payment of rents by cash strapped artists, and other problems. The large size of the building created large demands for funding, maintenance, and administration. Discussions began in the summer of reforming the Workspace program and of creating other programming solutions for the building. Only a handful of performances and one other group exhibition,A Month of Sundays(September 19October 10, 1976) were staged in P.S. 1 that year.
In December a fire at the Idea Warehouse forced the I.A.U.R. to give up that space. The Institute had disassociated itself from 10 Bleecker Street and returned the Coney Island site to the city, thus reducing the number of spaces to P.S. 1 and the Clocktower. Though the I.A.U.R. may have expected to continue finding new spaces for artists, if only for limited times, the acquisition of space had in fact come to an end.
19771979: An Increase in Programming
1977 saw the implementation of new programming produced by the discussions of the previous year. In January the first special projects opened. A set of rooms in the building, most or all on the second floor, were individually assigned to selected artists who then installed their artwork without supervision. Between ten and twenty artists usually participated in the program each season; they received mention in the seasonal press release and the I.A.U.R. produced a postcard for their show.
Another change was the transformation of the Workspace program into the National and International Studio Program. The National Program featured a juried selection process and charged selected artists a reduced rent for a year's tenancy. The International Program negotiated contracts with national cultural organizations of several countries. Those organizations pre-selected artists for final approval by the I.A.U.R., paid a fee for the studio, and supplied a stipend for the artist's stay in the United States. While these studio program changes were begun in 1977, the program formalized slowly. Through the next half decade national artists frequently rented studios for more than one year and initially most were still from New York City, though over time fewer applicants were familiar to the Institute. International participation grew slowly and comprised only a handful of artists in this time. Furthermore, it wasn't until 1984 that the national and international studio artists showed their work in a single annual group exhibition with a catalogue. Previously there had only been small group shows or individual artists had filtered into the Special Projects program or otherwise staged small exhibitions.
1977 also saw the formalization of the exhibition calendar for P.S. 1. The schedule featured four exhibition seasons, fall, early winter (November and December,) late winter (January and February,) and spring. Special projects, group exhibitions and other programs would share a single opening date. By 1981 the Institute switched over to a more consistent three season cycle of fall, winter, and spring. Meanwhile the Clocktower operated on a more irregular monthly or bimonthly rotation of exhibitions. Until 1997 no exhibitions were held during the summer months.
In the fall of 1978 another major programming initiative debuted. The Interdisciplinary or Multidisciplinary Program. A set of rooms in the school building were reserved each season for small curated exhibitions focused on specific media including film, video, photography, performance, dance, fashion, poetry, and architecture. Often the same individuals, such as Leandro Katz for film and Hollywood di Russo for fashion, curated their specific media for many years in a row.
Curated solo exhibitions and large group shows continued among these other programming initiatives. Significant group exhibitions in the late seventies include A Painting Show(May 2May 29, 1977,)New York Avant-Garde/Works and Projects of the Seventies(October 9November 6, 1977,)Indoor/Outdoor Sculpture Show(April 16May 21, 1978,) and Sound(September 30November 18, 1979) while solo exhibitions and programs at the P.S. 1 and the Clocktower included works by Jacki Apple, Jennifer Bartlett, Robert Ryman, Keith Sonnier, Min Tanaka, and many others.
The 1980s: International Activities
This pattern of programming would continue through the decade. Each exhibition season offered Special Projects, Interdisciplinary Projects, an exhibition of studio program participants, and curated group exhibitions and solo shows. The formal arrangement of Interdisciplinary Programming would stop by the end of the decade though sections such as architecture and fashion had ceased earlier. But Special Projects, studio program exhibitions, and the basic exhibition calendar persisted into the 1990s. During this period however the I.A.U.R. grew its involvement with international art. One source of involvement was the growth of the International Studio Program, but across the decade the Institute staged a succession of large and small exhibitions focused on art from other countries. One of the first such shows was Icebreakers: Contemporary Swedish Expressionists(November 11December 11, 1982) followed the next year by Expressions: New Art from Germany(September 25November 20, 1983) which helped introduce painters such as Georg Baselitz and Anselm Kiefer to an American audience.The Knot: Arte Povera at P.S. 1(October 6December 15, 1985) served the same role for contemporary Italian artists while in the spring of that same year exhibitions of Swedish photography, Mexican traditional art, and new art from Switzerland were held at P.S. 1. In 1986 Alanna Heiss curated an exhibition of the sculptor Isamu Noguchi at the 42nd Venice Biennale and in 1990 the exhibition Casin Fantasma(May 24July 15, 1990) at the 44th Venice Biennale. Exhibitions of international art and curatorial activities abroad remained an important part of the Institute through the 2000s.
The Clocktower continued presenting solo exhibitions (two at a time usually for a month run each) with occasional group shows and in the later 1980s staged a series of multi-part exhibitions examining a particular theme from multiple angles. These included the 19871988 four part The Pop Project; the 19881989 four part Here and There: Travels; the 1989 five part The Periphery; and the three part series CommuNYcation in 1990. The exhibition series concept was also carried out at P.S. 1 with 1987's Out of the Studio and 1988's Brazil Projects.
Finally, in 1988, the Institute and Art for Urban Resources changed its name to the Institute for Contemporary Art, P.S. 1 and the Clocktower Gallery. Despite using the name I.A.U.R. for sixteen years, the names of the locations, P.S. 1 and the Clocktower, seemed to be more commonly used. In 1976 and sporadically afterwards the I.A.U.R. had referred to P.S. 1 as Project Studios One and in the 1980s the name P.S. 1 Museum was tried out, but neither appellation persisted. Likewise now; despite the name change evidence is scant that the name Institute for Contemporary Art was much used practically.
The 1990s: Renovation and Reopening
The 1990s began much as the 1980s had proceeded. Significant exhibitions early in the decade included David Hammons: Rousing the Rubble, 19691990(December 16, 1990February 10, 1991) and Dennis Oppenheim: And the Mind Grew Fingers(December 8, 1991February 9, 1992)both of which travelled to other venues and the group show Slow Art: Painting in New York Now(April 26June 21, 1992.) Alanna Heiss curated a tribute to John Cage,The Swift Sound of Things: Cage & Co. at the 45th Venice Biennale in 1993. That fall P.S. 1 staged Stalin's Choice: Soviet Socialist Realism 19321956(November 21, 1993February 27, 1994.) Comprised entirely of works borrowed from institutions in the former Soviet Union during a period of political instability, the exhibition was a tremendous feat of planning and labor. Alanna Heiss' already busy European travel schedule was only compounded by Tunnel of Art, her project to mark the opening of the Channel Tunnel by bringing together artists for onsite conversations, and her curatorial work for the 1995 Lausanne Biennial in Switzerland.
In 1994 P.S. 1 began shutting its galleries for a long-planned and much needed renovation. When the building was first occupied in 1976 only the bare minimum of renovation was done. In the years since, P.S.1 had suffered chronic boiler issues, failing windows, flooding, and other structural deficiencies. The building also lacked an elevator, ramps, and loading dock for accessibility and art installing. The renovation designed by architect Frederick Fisher addressed those issues and also created space for a café and bookstore. Most importantly, Fisher's design turned the paved parking lot surrounded by a chain-link fence into a walled courtyard that served as the new main entry way. Previously, the public entrance was a small door on the building's western side that opened into a narrow stairwell. Now the public crossed the courtyard, ascended a wide stairs and entered through a bank of doors into a newly created foyer. The work was completed over the next three years. A handful of exhibitions appeared in the building in 1994 but none in 1995 and 1996. P.S. 1 also changed its name once again in advance of the reopening, now calling itself P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center.
The reopening in October 1997 was a significant event in the New York's cultural scene and produced a vast amount of national and international press coverage. Over two hundred artists participated in the ten separate group and solo exhibitions that opened on the same day. And with the reopening came new programs and initiatives. P.S. 1 had occasionally run educational programs for children and students but now ran more continuous and better funded classes and programs in renovated basement space. For the first time the exhibition calendar was year-round rather than simply spring, fall, and winter. To accompany summer exhibitions, in 1998 P.S. 1 staged the first series of weekend dance and music parties it named Warm Up and laid the foundation of what by 1999 developed into the Young Architects Program. The courtyard was also used for outdoor film programs and a themed family and community day of activities.
1999Present: The Merger with MoMA and Beyond
In February 1999, still energized from the reopening a year before, P.S. 1 announced its merger with The Museum of Modern Art. The merger would be a slow ten-year process and was designed so that P.S. 1 would retain significant independence from the Museum. The merger provided P.S. 1 with greater financial security, administrative support, and access to MoMA's development resources. In return, MoMA demonstrated its continuing dedication to contemporary art by gaining an outlet for exhibiting more experimental artwork and for featuring programming by younger and emerging artists. The main visible sign of the merger in 1999 was Philip Johnson's Dance Pavilion the architect designed for that summer's Warm Up.Greater New York(February 27May 30, 2000) was the first significant cooperative exhibition between the institutions. As a survey of young and emerging local artists, assembling the exhibition required a team of MoMA and PS1 curators to make numerous studio visits and sort through portfolios of hundreds of possible participants. In 2002, while rebuilding and expanding the 53rd street location, MoMA opened temporary galleries in Queens within walking distance of P.S. 1 offering more opportunities for cross-promotion and cooperative programming.
Through the 1990s the Clocktower Gallery had held fewer and fewer exhibitions (though they increased slightly in 1996 when P.S. 1 was closed.) The space was instead used as work space for the National and International Studio Program which also continued to occupy space at P.S. 1. The Clocktower's fitness for exhibitions was worsened by heightened security concerns in downtown Manhattan following the September 11th terror attacks, and in the first years of the new decade the studio program itself was being brought to a close. The likely reasons for ending the program include a greater number of similar programs in New York and around the country, scarcer funding, and a change in institutional priorities and interests. The National Studio Program ceased in 2003 and the International Program ended the following year with the exhibition Visa for Thirteen(April 25June 1, 2004.) The Clocktower was refurbished and in 2004 Alanna Heiss began a new program there, an internet radio station called WPS1 featuring programs by and about artists.
In 2008 the merger with MoMA was complete and that December Alanna Heiss retired as Director. She retained use of the Clocktower Gallery and continued operating WPS1, now renamed Art International Radio. Heiss also resumed physical exhibitions in the downtown space.
In 2009 Klaus Biesenbach was named Director, only the second in the institution's history, and in 2010 the name was changed again, to MoMA PS1. Biesenbach initiated a variety of new programming including Sunday Sessions in the outdoor performance dome, the "Summer School" educational program, as well as a general increase in the amount of performance and other events at PS1, resembling the variety and breadth of activity of the institution in the 1970s. Warm Up and YAP continue as annual events amid an active exhibition program, and the institution remains a leading center of contemporary art in New York City and the world.
A Note on Names
MoMA PS1 was founded as the Institute for Art and Urban Resources (I.A.U.R.) in 1972, the articles of incorporation being signed more than a year after The Brooklyn Bridge Event and months after exhibitions began at 10 Bleecker Street. The I.A.U.R. name was not officially superseded until 1988 and still existed in some legal documents through 1999. After the P.S. 1 school building opened in 1976 and only the Clocktower Gallery remained as an additional exhibition space, the institution came to be informally referred to by those names, either one or both together depending on the context, and this practiced continued through the 2000s. Even today, as the full name MoMA PS1 becomes more commonly used, the shorter term PS1 may still be predominant. Only when the MoMA PS1 name became official in 2010 did the periods disappear from the orthography, previously it was always spelled P.S. 1.
The MoMA PS1 Archives is so called in keeping with archival practice of using the most recent institutional name represented in the collection. In the finding aid the name I.A.U.R. is used in conjunction with any activities prior to the opening of the P.S. 1 school building in 1976. After that point the name P.S. 1 is used when discussing the entire organization, and that name or the Clocktower used when referring to activities at the specific location. The name MoMA PS1 and the abbreviation PS1 are used when referring to the organization's current activities or when reflecting on institutional history from a present-day perspective. Some inconsistencies may yet persist despite efforts to standardize usage.
Scope and Content
The MoMA PS1 Archives is the comprehensive organizational records of PS1 starting with the very beginnings of the founding organization, the Institute for Art and Urban Resources (I.A.U.R.), in 1971. The records provide extensive important documentary evidence of an institution that was in the vanguard of non-profit spaces and at the heart of the 1970s and 1980s New York art world, and that continues to be a vital center for the exploration and exhibition of contemporary art to this day. Documentation of particular historical significance in the Archives includes records of the institution's founding and growth in the early 1970s; exhibition and curatorial records for nearly nine hundred exhibitions and events over thirty-five years; records of the press and communications department, materials documenting the National and International Studio Program and the publications program, and records of the founder and director Alanna Heiss. Additional series contain records of educational activities, the WPS1 internet radio station, and general administrative records, for a total of nine major series, each broken down into various subseries as dictated by the records. Brief descriptions of each series follow below. For more specific descriptions, please consult the scope and content note at the beginning of each series and subseries.